A Guide to the Carroll County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-1912
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Carroll County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-1912
The Library of Virginia
Carroll County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-001-1912-078
Digital images
Carroll County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Digital images were generated by Backstage Library Works through the Circuit Court Records Preservation Program.
Historical Information
Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
Carroll County was named for Charles Carroll of Carrollton, a signer of the Declaration of Independence from Maryland. It was formed from Grayson County in 1842, and part of Patrick County was added in 1856. The county seat is Hillsville.
Scope and Content
Carroll County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1842-1912, are indexed into the Chancery Records Index. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, slave records, business records or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
Chancery cases are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
Arrangement
Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found. Arranged chronologically.
Arrangement of documents within each folder are as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Carroll County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia. See A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm
See the Chancery Records Index found on the Library of Virginia web site for the chancery records of other Virginia localities.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Carroll County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
African Americans--History.; Business enterprises--Virginia--Carroll County.; Debt--Virginia--Carroll County.; Divorce suits--Virginia--Carroll County.; Estates (Law)--Virginia--Carroll County.; Equity--Virginia--Carroll County.; Land subdivision--Virginia--Carroll County.; Slaves--Virginia--Carroll County.
Geographical Names:
Carroll County (Va.)--History.; Carroll County (Va.)--Genealogy.
Genre and Form Terms:
Chancery causes--Virginia--Carroll County.; Deeds--Virginia--Carroll County.; Judicial records--Virginia--Carroll County.; Land records--Virginia--Carroll County.; Local government records--Virginia--Carroll County.; Plats--Virginia--Carroll County.; Wills--Virginia--Carroll County.
Selected Suits of Interest
- 1866-005: Jesse Marion vs. Letitia Marion; 1866-006: Amos Bryant vs. Mary Bryant; 1866-011: Ephraim C. Wampler vs. Eliza Wampler; 1867-017: George W. Hendly vs. Jane Hendly; 1867-019: John T. Edwards vs. Isabella T. Edwards; 1868-018: Allen E. Bowers vs. Elizabeth W.G. Bowers; 1871-017: Julian Gordy vs. Sarah Gordy; and 1877-014: Wesley Sutphin vs. Lucy T. Sutphin:
  Plaintiffs served in the Confederate army during the Civil War. They returned home after the war and accused wives of adultery while they were away in the service.
- 1868-005: John Early and wife vs. William C. Thornton and wife, etc.:
  Documents in cause reference destruction of court records by Federal soldiers under the command of Major General Stoneman in April 1865.
- 1878-032: American Colonization Society vs. Edward Marshall:
  Will found in cause originally recorded in Philadelphia. ACS alleges that sheriff covertly withheld a tax bill with intent to force delinquency and sale of property, purchased by him. Deceased was native Virginian, former governor of Illinois, had been on ACS board of directors and was a longtime antislavery proponent. His will bequeathed a large tract of land to the ACS so the organization could sell it and use the proceeds to further its colonization efforts.
- 1880-051: Sparrel Huff, etc. v. John Collier, etc.:
  Peter Huff died intestate, but leaving several enslaved people, one of which "was assigned to his widow Mary for her lifetime, in pursuance of the statute then in force allowing a widow a life estate in one third of the slaves of which her husband dies possessed." Later, "the said slave, becoming unmanageable and impudent was by consent and agreement of all parties, sold." The widow was to receive interest annually on the sale (slave was sold for 570 dollars in 1853.)
- 1882-021: Thomas W. Bryant vs. Guardians of James McMurran:
  Cause involved recovering 13 years of expenses for caring for boy whose father joined the Union Army during the late war and died in service, leaving pensions to his heirs.
- 1882-034: Ellis Dalton Vs. Lucy J. Dalton:
  Husband seeks divorce from wife alleged of adultery, and who left for West Virginia while husband was "sick with the fever." When asked if she would at least come see him as he was very ill and may not survive, deposition notes that "before she would come one step back this way she would go ten thousand miles the other way."
- 1883-003: Joseph Norton vs. Sophina Norton:
  Husband seeks divorce due to wife's infidelity and giving birth to child three months after marriage and "attempting to destroy" child. Wife gave birth outdoors in the snow in the middle of the night and left the infant near a log under some snow. Infant's frozen body was found the next day. Wife claimed she had been raped. She later fled Virginia.
- 1886-009: Alexander Smith vs. Martha F. Williams:
  Defendant's husband was still alive in Washington County. Depositions reference a divorce cause involving the defendant heard in Grayson County. See also Grayson County Chancery Cause 1860-039: Matilda Williams vs. William Williams.
- 1893-027: Milton Stoneman vs. John W. Stoneman, etc.:
  Wife of complainant died leaving property to her sons, and giving her husband lifetime rights to a portion. Will also directs sons to care for their father. Complainant charges that the sons are not doing so. Interesting cause where husband has no property or means of support other than that bequeathed by his wife.
- 1896-021: Elizabeth Dalton vs. Isaac Jennings:
  Plaintiff alleges that land sold by late husband was sold after her marriage so she believes she is due a dower interest. Depositions reference War of 1812 and Civil War. Transcript of Chancery Cause 1855-003: James Stafford etc. vs. Reuben Dalton etc.
- 1903-019: A.W. Westmoreland vs. Laura A. Westmoreland:
  Plaintiff claimed Laura Westmoreland moved to Utah "where she still lives in adultery and for aught he knows she may there in the land of Joe Smith and Brigham Young be trying to substitute the practice of polyandry for the more ancient practice of polygamy."
- 1903-041: Nancy E. Worrell, etc. vs. James A. Worrell and wife:
  Nancy Worrell was mother of James A. Worrell. They made a contract that James would take care of her in her old age. James moved to Idaho seeking better opportunities. Cause includes correspondence between mother and son. Nancy pleaded with her son to return home. James wrote back saying he will never return describing saying Idaho was much better than Virginia was. The cause was dismissed at request of Nancy because her son returned home.
- 1904-069 and 1906-003: W.E. Jennings vs. Emily Jennings:
  Emily Jennings was formerly married to John Oliver who left the state and was believed to be dead. He returned shortly after Emily married W.E. Jennings.